Adaline Pendleton Satterthwaite papers SSC.MS.00519
Sophia Smith Collection
Adaline Pendleton Satterthwaite papers
1917-2005
1917-2003
Sophia Smith Collection
Satterthwaite, Adaline Pendleton
SSC.MS.00519
33 boxes (16 linear feet)
Physician; Birth control advocate. The papers include extensive correspondence, diaries, medical records and reports, photographs, writings, and subject files pertaining to Satterthwaite's career as a physican, birth control pioneer, and internationally renowned expert in family planning. The collection is rich in materials documenting Satterthwaite's work in family planning in Puerto Rico, Bangladesh, Pakistan, and China.
Biographical / Historical
Adaline Pendleton Satterthwaite was born on 6 February 1917 in Berkeley, California to Jessie Larimore and John Lewis Pendleton. She graduated magna cum laude from Pomona College in 1937 with a B.S. in chemistry, and earned her M.D. degree in obstetrics and gynecology in 1942 from the University of California at San Francisco. She met her future husband, William Satterthwaite, also a doctor, in 1944 while working in San Juan, Puerto Rico; the couple had one son, David. In 1947 Satterthwaite and her family traveled to China as medical missionaries where she was involved in Barefoot Doctors, a UNICEF program that trained villagers to administer basic medical care to their communities. She continued her work in China following the death of William Satterthwaite in 1949, returning to the U.S. in 1951. From 1952 to 1967 she again lived in Puerto Rico, working as resident physician at Ryder Memorial Hospital, and it was during this time that she was struck by the plight of women who had more children than they could support. She subsequently became involved in running some of the first clinical trials for oral contraceptives, and her data was instrumental in the FDA decision to approve the Pill in 1960. Satterthwaite also conducted pioneering research developing the intrauterine device (IUD). As she became more expert in the realm of maternal child health and international family planning, Satterthwaite was employed by various organizations, including the Ford Foundation, the Population Council of the Rockefeller Foundation, and the United Nations Fund for Population Activities under whose auspices she lived and worked in Thailand, Pakistan, Bangladesh, Mexico, and Venezuela. In the early 1980s she shifted from full-time work to short-term consulting projects in such countries as Mauritius, the Dominican Republic, Colombia, Peru, and Nepal.
In the late 1980s, upon retiring and relocating to Langhorne, Pennsylvania to be near her son and his family, Satterthwaite became an active volunteer in numerous organizations. She served on the board of directors of the Institute for Development Training, the Medical College of Pennsylvania, Planned Parenthood of Bucks County, the Newtown Friends School, and the Bucks County YWCA. She was also involved with the American Public Health Association, the League of Women Voters of Bucks County, Physicians for Social Responsibility, Meals on Wheels, and the Middletown Society of Friends. She used her fluency in Spanish to translate for patients at local hospitals, and as a tutor for the Latino Leadership Alliance of Bucks County. In 2002 Satterthwaite received the Bucks County Women's History Award for her contributions to the community. Her professional awards included the National Council for International Health Award, the Women's Health Award of the American Medical Women's Association, and the Margaret Sanger Award of Planned Parenthood of Bucks County. Satterthwaite published widely in professional journals throughout her career. She died in 2005.
Scope and Contents
The Adaline Pendleton Satterthwaite Papers consist of 16 linear ft. dating from 1917 to 2003. Types of materials include diaries, photographs, legal and financial documents, reports, case studies, articles, newspaper clippings, charts and statistics, notes, newsletters, printed materials, brochures, pamphlets, and memorabilia.
The bulk of the papers date from the early 1950s through the late 1990s and focus on Satterthwaite's career as an obstetrician/gynecologist and internationally-known expert in maternal child health and family planning. Major topics found in these papers include the development of modern methods of birth control, notably the Pill, the IUD, Depo-Provera, and permanent sterilization for both men and women; infant and maternal morbidity and mortality in developing countries, particularly as related to pregnancy, childbirth, and multiple, unplanned pregnancies; the prevention and treatment of diarrhea, especially among children; and population control as a global priority. Satterthwaite concluded early in her career that family planning and maternal and child health were critical to world economic and political stability, and her efforts to address these issues are well-documented throughout the collection.
While Satterthwaite's letters to her husband are intimate and personal, her correspondence to family and friends is intended for a broader audience. It offers rich insight into daily life in foreign countries, including observations about local cultures, as well as the particulars of Satterthwaite's daily life. The correspondence of Satterthwaite's brother, Robert, who lived and worked for many years in Central and South America, is also of interest.
The diaries provide a detailed and intelligent account of Satterthwaite's many years of practice as a doctor, medical advisor, program director, and consultant to various world health organizations. They cover the time period beginning with her appointment as Resident Medical Advisor to the Population Council in Thailand in1966, through completion of her term of employment as Program Adviser to the Bangladesh Association for Voluntary Surgical Contraception in 1990. The remaining diaries, dating from mid-1990 to 1994, tend towards brevity and are generally concerned with the more mundane aspects of post-retirement daily life. This series also contains Satterthwaite's published articles, speeches and unpublished essays, as well as sermons by Rev. G. Arthur Canaday.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into five series:
I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS (1917-2003)
II. CORRESPONDENCE (1923-2001)
III. WRITINGS (1958-2000)
IV. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES (1938-2000)
V. SUBJECT FILES (1956-2000)
OVERSIZE MATERIALS
Conditions Governing Access
The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Adaline Pendleton Satterthwaite Papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2005 by her son, David Satterthwaite.
Abortion--History--Sources; Birth control--Developing countries--History--20th century--Sources; Contraceptives--Research--Sources; Gynecology--United States--History--Sources; Human reproduction--Social aspects--History--20th century; Missionaries, Medical--Africa--History--Sources; Missionaries, Medical--China--20th century; Obstetrics--History--Sources; Sterilization (birth control)--History--Sources; Women's health services--History--Sources; Women--Health and hygiene--History--Sources; China--Social conditions--1949-1976--Sources; Women--Puerto Rico--Social conditions--Sources; Women--Pakistan--Social conditions--Sources; Women--Bangladesh--Social conditions--Sources; Appointment books; articles; Awards; Biographical sketches; Brochures; clippings; Contact sheets; correspondence; diaries; Genealogies; Greeting cards; Legal documents; Medical records; Negatives; Notes; photographs; Plaques; Resumes; scrapbooks; Wills; Writings; Yearbooks; Satterthwaite, Adaline Pendleton
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Scrapbooks, 1930s-40s (Box 1-2)
  - Clippings, 1985-2002 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Resumes, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Passports and biographical statements, 1947-90; undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Prayers and inspirational sayings, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Education
    - High school yearbook, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Pomona College 50th reunion, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - University of California San Francisco Medical School 50th reunion, 1991-93 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Continuing medical education: correspondence and certificates, 1970s-90s (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Photographs: Satterthwaite alone, and with family and friends, 1917-90s, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Medical licensure
    - United States, 1980s-2000s (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Puerto Rico, 1985-95 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Legal and financial
    - Personal documents, 1948-2001; undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Anne M. Pendleton Trust, 1982-99 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Harry and Julia Abramson Fund, 1994-99 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
    - Lois Pendleton Todd Medical Scholarship (Stanford University Medical School), 1982-92 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Assistance to international friends (Box 4)
      - Ahmed, Kabir, 1981-82 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - D'Costa family, 1981-2001 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Haque, Anwaral, 1981-2001 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Tabarias, Winston, 1991-2001 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Others, 1981-98 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Honors and awards [see also Oversize Materials]
    General
    [see also Oversize Materials]
    - Medical College of Pennsylvania, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - National Council for International Health, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Pomona College, 1987-91 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Other, 1967-2003; undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Plaques, 1965-2002 (Box 5)
    - Glass, 1998; undated (Box 6)
  - Family members
    - Larimore, Adaline Ann, circa 1934 (APS grandmother) (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Morris, William: "William Morris and His Family" by Mary Morris Godfrey Embleton, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Pendleton, Anne Miltimore: memorial booklet, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Pendleton, Jessie Larimore (APS mother): obituary and correspondence re: last illness and death, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Pendleton, Morris (APS brother): obituaries and condolences, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      [see also SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE]
    - Pendleton, Robert (APS brother): anecdotes, 1957; undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Satterthwaite, David (APS son): photographs, and printed materials, 1990s; undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Satterthwaite, William (APS husband): anecdotes, 1949; undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Todd, Lois Pendleton: biographical statement, photographs, book, and clippings re: husband Oliver J. Todd, 1931-99, undated (APS sister) (Box 7, Folder 9-10)
    - Larimore, Morris and Pendleton family: photograph and genealogies, 1966; undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Travel: China
    - Correspondence and travel documents, 1983-84 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Newsletters, 1984-86 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Printed materials, 1971-86 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Photographs
    - Friends, 1950s-90s (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Negatives, circa 1960s-90s (Box 8, Folder 5)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Personal
    - Galley, Esther T., 1980-81 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Pendleton, John L. and Jessie L., 1923-51 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Pendleton, Morris B., 1949-84 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Pendleton, Robert, 1945-47 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Satterthwaite, William, 1944-45 (Box 9, Folder 3-12)
    - Shea, Randall (Witness for Peace) (Box 9)
      - 1993-96 (Box 9, Folder 13)
      - 1997-2001, undated (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
    - Family and friends (Box 10)
      - 1928-69 (Box 10, Folder 3-8)
      - 1970-2001, undated (Box 11, Folder 1-8)
    - Holiday cards, 1950-93 (Box 12, Folder 1-3)
  - Congressional representatives, 1991-97 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - General
    [see also SERIES IV. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES]
    - 1979-94 (Box 12, Folder 5-9)
    - 1995-2001, undated (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
  - Mailing lists, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS
  - Diaries
    - Taipei and Thailand, 1966 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Pakistan and Thailand, 1967 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Pakistan, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - New York and Pakistan, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Pakistan, 1970-71 (Box 14, Folder 5-7)
    - Peru and Venezuela, 1972 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Venezuela and Bangaldesh, 1973 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Dominican Republic and Mexico, Jan - Oct 1974 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Bangladesh (Box 15)
      - Nov - Dec 1974, Nov 1976-77 (Box 15, Folder 3-6)
      - 1978-83 (Box 16, Folder 1-5)
    - Life and work in other parts of the world (Box 16)
      - 1985 (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - 1986-90 (Box 17, Folder 1-8)
      - 1991-94 (Box 18, Folder 1-4)
  - Published articles, 1959-82 (Box 18, Folder 5-6)
  - Essays and speeches, 1958-2000; undated (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Unidentified fragments, undated (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Writings by others: sermons by Rev. G Arthur Casaday, 1967-68 (Box 19, Folder 1)
- SERIES IV. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES
  - Medical missionary work
    - Articles, newsletters, and printed materials, 1938-82; undated (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions: LuHo Hospital, Tungchow, China (Box 19)
      - Photographs, clippings, and printed materials, 1943-59 (Box 19, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence (in Chinese), circa late, 1940s (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Maternal and child health, and family planning
    - American Public Health Association consultancy: correspondence, financial information, contracts, forms and printed materials, 1981-94 (Box 19, Folder 5)
      [see also SERIES V. SUBJECT FILES: birth control: oral contraceptives in developing countries]
    - Association for Voluntary Surgical Contraception: Bangladesh (Box 19)
      - Correspondence and travel itinerary, 1987-88 (Box 19, Folder 6)
      - Reports, 1981-92 (Box 19, Folder 7-12)
      - "Procedure Manual for the Surgical Team Providing Tubal Occlusion and Vasectomy,", 1989 (Box 19, Folder 13)
      - Printed materials, 1987-91 (Box 19, Folder 14)
    - Ford Foundation, Bangladesh: correspondence and reports, 1982 (Box 19, Folder 15)
    - Population Council (Box 19)
      [see also SERIES III. WRITINGS: Diaries, 1966-74]
      - Bangladesh: Taylor-Berelson Project: photographs and reports, 1974-78 (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - Pakistan: reports, 1967-71 (Box 20, Folder 2-3)
      - Thailand (Box 20)
        - Reports and photographs, 1966-67 (Box 20, Folder 4-5)
        - Trip to Indonesia: clippings and photographs, 1966 (Box 20, Folder 6)
        - Trip to Iran: photograph and speech, 1966 (Box 20, Folder 7)
      - Venezuela, 1971-73 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Puerto Rico, Commonwealth of (Box 20)
      - Articles and clippings, 1947-57; undated (Box 20, Folder 9)
      - Pamphlets and brochures, 1953-59; undated (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Ryder Memorial Hospital (Box 21)
        - Pamphlets and printed materials, 1956-89 (Box 21, Folder 2)
        - Correspondence, 1952-66 (Box 21, Folder 3)
        - Photographs, 1950s-65 (Box 21, Folder 4)
        - Birth control and other gynecological and obstetrical issues: reports, charts, statistics, and notes, 1956-64 (Box 21, Folder 5-6)
        - Oral contraceptive clinical trials (includes data re: the IUD) (Box 21)
          - Reports by Satterthwaite, 1961-63 (Box 21, Folder 7)
          - Writings by others, 1995-98 (Box 21, Folder 8-9)
        - Farewell tribute, 1965 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - United Nations Fund for Population Activities
      - Bangladesh (Box 21)
        [see also SERIES V. SUBJECT FILES]
        - Dacca (Box 21)
          - Correspondence, 1974-81 (Box 22, Folder 1)
          - Photographs, 1977-81 (Box 22, Folder 2-3)
          - Performance reviews, 1977-79 (Box 22, Folder 4)
          - Population control and family planning (Box 22)
            - "Five Year Plan,", 1980 (Box 22, Folder 5)
            - Reports, 1980-82 (Box 22, Folder 6-8)
            - Printed materials, 1980-83 (Box 22, Folder 9)
        - Matlab Project (in partnership with International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research)
          - Contracts and correspondence, 1981-84 (Box 22, Folder 10)
          - Charts, forms, and notes, 1980-82 (Box 22, Folder 11)
          - "Drug Dosage Book,", undated (Box 22, Folder 12)
          - Case studies and reports (Box 22)
            - Health Services Project, 1983 (Box 22, Folder 13)
            - Maternal Mortality Study (by Lyn Singer), 1983-84 (Box 23, Folder 1)
            - Other, 1982-83 (Box 23, Folder 2)
          - Charts, diagrams, and memorabilia, circa 1982 (includes urine sample) (Box 23, Folder 3)
          - Abortion, IUD, Depo-Provera: articles and reports, 1980-89 (Box 23, Folder 4)
          - International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research (Box 23)
            - Correspondence, memoranda and reports, 1980-86 (Box 24, Folder 1)
            - Conferences and annual reports, 1982-89 (Box 24, Folder 2)
            - Newsletters, 1995-2000 (Box 24, Folder 3)
        - Miscellaneous reports and printed materials, 1983-89 (Box 24, Folder 4)
        - Munshiganj Project: reports, 1984 (Box 24, Folder 5)
        - APS visit to Gafargaon Women's College, 14 Apr 1988 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - UNFPA (in partnership with Center for Population and Family Health at Columbia University): Nepal
      - Correspondence, 1987-92 (Box 24, Folder 7)
      - Program description, 1980-88 (Box 24, Folder 8)
      - Financial information, 1987-88 (Box 24, Folder 9)
      - Reports (Box 24)
        - 1979 (Box 24, Folder 10)
        - 1982-87, undated (Box 25, Folder 1-3)
      - Family Planning and Child Study Project: forms, undated (Box 25, Folder 4)
      - Maps and printed materials, 1985-87 [see also Oversize Materials] (Box 25, Folder 5)
      - Articles, 1982-91 (Box 25, Folder 6)
      - Clippings, 1985 [see also Oversize Materials] (Box 25, Folder 7)
      - Center for Population and Family Health: general information, 1989-90 (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - World Neighbors: Peru
      - Proposal, 1982 (Box 25, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence, 1983-88 (Box 25, Folder 10)
      - Financial information, 1984 (Box 25, Folder 11)
      - Reports, 1984; 1989 (Box 25, Folder 12)
      - Charts and statistical information (Box 26, Folder 1)
      - Notes and forms, 1983-84 (Box 26, Folder 2-3)
      - Articles, clippings, and printed materials, 1984-87; undated (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Post-retirement
    - Child Health Foundation, 1986-98 (Box 26)
      - Board of Trustees files: notes, 1986-99 (Box 26, Folder 5)
      - Annual reports and newsletters, 1991-98 (Box 26, Folder 6)
      - Projects and proposals, 1992-98 (Box 26, Folder 7)
      - Clippings and press releases, 1988-95 (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - Institute for Training and Development (Box 26)
      - Statements of purpose and strategic plans, 1989-2000 (Box 26, Folder 9)
      - General correspondence, 1987-93 (Box 26, Folder 10)
      - Board of Directors files: correspondence and memoranda, agendas, and minutes (Box 26, Folder 11)
        - 1988-89 (Box 26)
        - 1990-96 (Box 27, Folder 1-3)
      - Financial information, 1990-98 (Box 27, Folder 4)
      - Newsletters and printed materials, 1992-2000 (Box 27, Folder 5)
      - Projects and proposals (Box 27)
        - HIV/AIDS, 1992-93 (Box 27, Folder 6)
        - Video productions, 1990s (Box 27, Folder 7)
        - Women's health, 1990-93 (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Planned Parenthood of Bucks County (Pennsylvania) (Box 27)
      - General correspondence, 1992-94 (Box 28, Folder 1)
      - Abortion Task Force: agendas, minutes, and financial information, 1993-94 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - Affiliate Medical Committee: agendas, minutes, and financial information, 1992-96 (Box 28, Folder 3-4)
      - Newsletters and brochures, 1992-95 (Box 28, Folder 5)
- SERIES V. SUBJECT FILES
  - Abortion, 1991-93 (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - Adoption, 1994-95; undated (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - Bangladesh, 1984-94; undated (Box 28, Folder 8)
  - Birth control
    - General, 1964-91 (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - Oral contraception in developing countries (Box 28)
      - Correspondence, notes and reports, 1984 (Box 28, Folder 10)
        [see also SERIES IV. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES: American Public Health Association]
      - Charts and statistics, 1982-84 (Box 28, Folder 11)
      - "Effects of Oral Contraceptive Use on Serum Lipids,", 1981-84 (Box 28, Folder 12)
      - "Tentative Program for 'Expert Meeting on Oral Contraceptive Needs of Developing Countries',", 1978-88 (Box 28, Folder 13)
      - Other articles, and printed materials, 1982-89 (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Child health, 1982-99; undated (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Childbirth, undated (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Choice in dying, 1996 (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Family planning and world population growth, 1960-2000; undated (Box 29, Folder 5-10)
  - HIV/AIDS, 1996 (Box 29, Folder 11)
  - Human rights, 1990; undated (Box 29, Folder 12)
  - India: Padhar Hospital, 1992-94 (Box 29, Folder 13)
  - League of Women Voters of Bucks County (Pennsylvania)
    - Population Coalition, 1966-2000; undated (Box 30, Folder 1-3)
    - Publications and printed materials, 1997 (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - Medical issues and conditions (general), 1986-92 (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Peace and nuclear disarmament
    - Canberra Commission (Australia), 1997 (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Physicians for Social Responsibility and International Physicians for the Prevention of Nuclear War, 1984-97 (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Printed materials, 1983-2000; undated (Box 30, Folder 8-9)
  - Politics, 1981-97; undated (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Religion
    - General, 1988-93; undated (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Langhorne (Pennsylvania) Presbyterian Church, 1992-96 (Box 31, Folder 3-4)
    - Quakers and others, 1969-2001 (Box 31, Folder 5)
  - Teen sex and teen violence, 1992-93 (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - Thailand, 1981-82 (Box 31, Folder 7)
  - Women's issues and organizations, 1969-92; undated (Box 31, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous and unidentified documents, 1956-98; undated (Box 31, Folder 9-10)
- Oversize Materials
  - Biographical materials (Box 32)
    - Clippings, 1950s-80s (Box 32)
    - Honors and awards, 1964; undated (Box 32)
  - Subject files
    - Abortion: NYT article on late term abortion, 1993 (Box 32)
    - Birth control: magazines, 1957-93 (Box 32)
    - Family planning and world population growth: clipping, 1981 (Box 32)
    - Teen sex and teen violence: clippings, 1993 (Box 32)
    - Thailand: clipping, 1982 (Box 32)
  - Posters and medical charts, 1964-98 (Map-case Flat file)
- Biographical Materials, 1917-2003; 4 linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains scrapbooks, and photographs of Satterthwaite and her family and friends; newspaper clippings about Satterthwaite and her work; financial information, including documentation of her involvement in several charitable enterprises; and honors and awards. Materials describing the lives of Satterthwaite's sister, Lois Pendleton Todd (also a physician), and her two brothers, Morris and Robert Pendleton, are also included, as are a small amount of genealogical information and materials documenting a return trip to China in 1984.
- Correspondence, 1923-2001; 2.25 linear feet
  This series, which spans Satterthwaite's entire professional life, is comprised of letters to and from Satterthwaite and her family and friends. Her own correspondence consists of detailed letters describing her life and work in various foreign countries. Correspondence with her husband, William Satterthwaite, is filed separately, and letters to and from friends and other family members have been combined (unless there is a significant amount to or from a particular individual, as in the case of Randall Shea, a volunteer for Witness for Peace). Many of the holiday cards contain news from overseas from friends involved in missionary and other types of philanthropic work, informing and elaborating on Satterthwaite's own correspondence.
- Writings, 1958-2000; 2.25 linear feet